my third and final point of disagreement
or major point of disagreement is to do
with religion and Christianity and let
me start by reiterating that I think
what he's done with the Bible stories is
remarkable I've learned a huge amount
from what I've seen at those lectures I
haven't watched all of I've watched
about half of them but I've learned a
huge amount from what I've seen from
those lectures and once again the way he
draws in other sources to create this
broad perspective from which to view
them has been for me anyway entirely
original and and a wonderful thing
however specifically with Christianity
and this is the religion with which he
most clearly identifies himself
obviously I don't think that's I don't
think that's open to dispute has at its
core something which I think is
profoundly damaging and and I would like
to explore a little bit here so I'm
pretty sure it's in a story of Noah that
God undertakes to man never to do the
whole flood thing ever again and gives
him dominion over the earth and over the
animals and so um you know this story
along with I suspect many others I'm no
biblical scholar I don't I don't know
the Bible well reinforces something
which sneers at the very very very core
of Christianity which is an idea of
separation between God man and nature
it's like a triumvirate of three
separate things that God created nature
God created man God inserted man into
nature and God gave man dominion over
nature and these ideas which I think run
deep deep deep in the psyche of the
Western mind are responsible in my
opinion for a huge amount of the
external and internal destruction going
on
moment to give you an idea of what I'm
talking about the or a better idea sure
I should say what I'm talking about in
the Eastern philosophies in Buddhism for
example God or the Buddha or whatever is
is in all things right I mean all things
both animate and inanimate as we would
call them contain within them the Buddha
and so what you do to the world around
you you also do to yourself it's one
continuous interconnected inseparable
thing and you know every single thing is
a manifestation of God is a
manifestation of the Buddha and as I
said that which you do to your world you
do in a very very real way to yourself
because you are the world and the world
is you and to me this connectedness with
the world around you with nature with
everybody else seeing all things as God
manifest in physical form or whatever
III think this is absent from
Christianity and is for me the biggest
reason not to be of that I mean I listen
the teachings of Jesus Christ the
brotherhood of man and forgiveness and
tolerance and understanding and love and
all of that absolutely all on board with
that he was by no means the first person
to preach that kind of thing but the the
mythology that underlies it and that
separation of God from man from nature
and again I'm quite willing to accept
that there is a deficiency in my own
understanding of Christianity like I
said I am no scholar but that that does
seem to me to be and I'm not the only
one to think this as Joseph
Oh God his name escapes me
begins with the see I can't think of his
name it'll come to me anyway talks about
this also about this failing in
Christianity that it fails to appreciate
the divine in all things you know that
all things have a soul all beings have a
soul is not unique to man and this sense
of superiority that man has and that he
has the right to impose his will through
force over nature in order to make life
better for him alright I think is really
you know because it encourages - it
encourages us to see the world a bunch
of stuff out there that we can use any
way that we like and that seems to me to
be right at the heart of how we are able
to treat the world as we do and I'm not
talking about climate change just like
mr. Peterson I have deep suspicions
about the climate change narrative which
is being forced down my throat just for
the very simple reason that it's being
forced down my throat that makes me
extremely suspicious but there is no
doubt that the amount of plastic we're
throwing into the ground into the ends
of the water the toxification of
freshwater supplies the stripping the
forests the d the you know the loss of
soil as a consequence of deforestation
the chemical runoff the blah blah blah
means that there's a there's a million
things all of which need urgent
attention you know species die-off there
are many many things all of which need
urgent attention and for me the climate
change narrative is once again a
distraction from doing anything about
all of these things which actually there
are ready available solutions to instead
we're too busy squabbling about who's
right over climate change but anyway
that to one side that narrative and
again for the two mr. Peterson thank you
for integrate
on earth no it's not Conrad anyway thank
you again for introducing me to the idea
of the power of story to shape not only
our reality but the way that we function
in the world and but I but I do think
adhering to and internalizing flawed
stories is extremely dangerous and and
for me the judeo-christian narrative of
God man nature is is is deeply deeply
fought it encourages us to exploit and
destroy the world around us and not to
honor cherish worship it in every action
that in every action interaction that we
take with it there is no way if we saw
every being as having a soul very much
like our own that we would treat our
livestock the way that we do for example
you know we love our pets and yet we go
down and we buy steaks anyway again it's
not really a thing I want to get into
but but I hope I've made my point but it
was Joseph Campbell I was talking about
not Joseph Conrad he wrote part of
darkness of course
Joseph Campbell was also very intimately
on his whole life exploring mythology
from all over the world in particular
looking for similarities cross-cultural
cross temporal similarities and then
looking at differences in order to
isolate what was cultural and what was
you know deeply embedded in the human
psyche not dissimilar to well in fact
was informed by Jung's work as is Jordan
Peterson so one of the points that
Campbell makes is that when things are
changing very rapidly it's impossible
for new mythologies
to emerge because it obviously takes
time for them to find expression and you
know he was he was writing primarily
back in the 60s 70s but the saying is
absolutely true today even more so that
things are changing so quickly that is
that it's all but impossible for new
myths new stories to develop but I guess
if there is an overarching point to this
video then it would be a plea for people
to try and let will make room for the
possibility of new stories in their
minds and in their
because the ones that we currently have
our stories of money are stories of
judeo-christian tradition our stories of
power and so on are all rooted in what
Charles Eisenstein refers to as the
story of separation where you know as
I've already talked about you know the
world's a bunch of stuff out there which
is which is for us to use and where
we're not in any way personally
connected with it in our stories don't
allow us to be you know we see
everything in physical terms that we
ourselves our awareness our
consciousness is nothing more than the
consequence of chemical reactions taking
place atoms and electrons and you know
waves of energy moving according to
deterministic laws and I mean I can't
prove it otherwise but my own experience
doesn't feel like that nobody's
experience feels like that and so you
know if it looks like a dark and smells
like a duck it's a duck or whatever the
phrase is is something like that it
escapes me exactly where it is so yeah
we really need to start coming up with
circulating reinforcing telling
ourselves new kinds of stories where the
underlying substrate is one of
connectedness and not of separation
because however much you deny the
reality of the fact that we are
connected to everything around us
everything around us if you know we're
part of it and it's part of us even if
you don't believe that it doesn't stop
it being true it doesn't stop the
consequences of our actions being
devastating ultimately to ourselves and
so you know if for nothing other than
self-interest we really need to start
developing some new stories anyway I'm
starting to repeat myself so thank you
very much for those of you that are
watching for watching and if you think
I'm saying interesting things then
please spread the word I guess
ultimately what I'm hoping is that this
gets back to Jordan Peters him himself
at Jordan Peters and himself and you
know that he thinks from worthy of
consideration and
most of them in some way but you know
that's unlikely who the am i 42
subscribers right so anyway thank you
very much for watching I'll make
something else soon